good things great things and sometimes
the most amazing things it all can
happen if you want it to happen and I
think now is the moment meditation
workout cooking and much more we're
giving you everything that you need
being back at home with wellness 360 at
home brought to you by ICS yellow bar
welcome again to yet another episode we
give giving you something really amazing
something that might just make you think
and maybe rectify a lot more so everyone
who is watching us life on this link and
on Facebook and Instagram
welcome to wellness 360 at home yet
again my name is Nathaniel Bhatia next
one hour I'm sure you will take back
something very special so what really is
happening and who is our guest today
we'll talk about the mental health this
is one criteria that we all need to
address seven point eight percent of
people across India are suffering
through mental health and how to get out
of it anxiety depression bipolar and
there are many names and more than that
their panic attacks so how do we address
this so we got somebody to make sure
that all your questions are answered in
a format that is well suited for
everyone who's watching us back home or
wherever you are Dibley a tip to
generated cove in nineteen and beyond
joining us today is somebody who masters
this well it's time that I welcome right
now well she's a certified counselor a
certified transpersonal regression
therapist and member of earth and NLP a
practitioner and certified neurofeedback
technician she is among the first to add
neurofeedback in her clinic in India
with driving center for mental and
emotional wellness in the heart of
Mumbai she's one of the most prominent
voices of mental wellness having spoken
nationally on numerous platforms
she's also a regular columnist our
business world in a consulting practice
just been an instrumental in setting up
and aligning startups as well as
counseling practices with organizations
communities and educational institutes
if we are delightful to welcome
sure at wellness 360 at home with ICS in
Lombard the one and only
Proctor tipo de right now have property
good to see you and welcome to 12 Ness
360 how are you doing this evening
great methen lovely to see you and
congratulations on this whole title of
wellness 360 I think it's fabulous given
the fact that wellness is what really
matters in not only these days but not
us all the time so really thank you for
having me I'm very excited about this
conversation going forward I think it's
a conversation that is needed every
single day and I think that if you
maximize your learning with what we're
doing today I think that you are set in
life and not just beyond akavit but set
for life in good measure and good health
and good values that will uphold your
entire well-being 360 I like how you
said property it's just not about this
scenario right now the crisis but for a
long run in your life you can actually
get a good balance and of course we will
address a main subject about whoa be
prepared for coab 819 are we prepared or
can we get prepared so this to all of us
today our wellness 360 at home is gonna
be a little bit of a moderated doing
well I'm gonna ask questions on certain
topics and faculty will address all our
answers regarding the question so let's
get it started the mental health
resilience it's something that you know
what everybody wants to know about the
first question that I wanna ask you pump
day is about self-care under coab it 19
so this is really relevant because all
my other answers will be looped to this
self-care is the most important aspect
of your well-being if you understand
what guy what is going on
in your mind and how do you address
what's going on in your mind to make it
a positive system I think you are set
for a successful life system so what
this really means is when we're looking
at our entire self-care we look II get
feelings what really are we feeling what
are the triggers to what we're feeling
how is our behavior getting changed or
adaptive given the feelings that we
experience now I'm gonna say some very
generalized statements only because of
the fact that I do believe that in India
we still have gender roles and self-care
means taking time out for yourself to be
able to give you that currently I know
you said 7.5% or 7.8 percent it's far
higher in terms of mental health or
illnesses and mental distress anxiety
and stress are also linked to mental
health distress and our experience or my
experience in this domain has sort of
made me recognize that you may have
mental health illnesses that you didn't
even know about there may be triggers of
stress that he didn't really pay
attention to but in these times it kind
of gets aggravated and really just being
the kind of person who listens to
yourself is what the key steps are so
when we really talk about mental health
and our own self-care we really need to
focus on the five elements of well-being
number one is your mindset so really
what is your mindset how do you focus on
bringing your mind to become
constructive and to aging so get rid of
the unhelpful get rid of the irrational
thoughts that keep popping up and focus
on the rational how do you then even try
to do this without having the barrier
the other verticals in playing the other
verticals are your choice when it comes
to your nutrition your choice when it
comes to your physical fitness your
choice when it comes to your recovery
because these elements are what make you
well know wellness 360
mindset nutrition physical fitness as
well as recovery so people who say that
I'm feeling great I'm feeling fit but
haven't had a good night's rest I'm not
going to be able to work effectively or
to have to reserve of energy to work or
to move in your day and make sure your
interactions are positive when you feel
stressed I know I have three children
and when I come back from work on a
regular day before covet 90 I would be
really stressed and I would need that
time to unwind and if I didn't get that
time to unwind I would be irritable and
it's unfair because I need to understand
my own reserve of energy to be able to
give the best of myself in any situation
your well-being arc is the arc of
nutrition exercise as well as recovery
that enables you to keep your mind well
the choices that you make in this are
extremely important and I I want to say
this again because a lot of people will
say you know it sounds kind of like you
know you need to have space to do
exercise you don't the moment you have
enough space to lie down you have space
to do planks you have place to do
push-ups if you have a place to sit you
have place to do a squat this is
well-being when it comes to physical
well-being some people have asked me in
the past how can we talk about food you
know some of us don't have any choice in
food right so there are people who have
choice that people who don't have
choices are talking about the spectrum
of people you have always got a choice
you have a choice and also one of the
most important things to recognize here
is that Donna is available to everybody
not all is nutritious it's important
that you choose the nutritious food also
I'm going to recognize that if you are
not moving that much if you are not
burning that much you must measure the
amount you eat through the amount you're
actually consuming in terms of in your
living and marry the two because if
you're overeating and really have very
little energy that you're expending
chances are you weight put on weight the
moment you put on weight
there is another mental health cycle
that takes place that doesn't make you
feel very good about yourself so it's
also a check in balance
in fact all these things we cannot
motivate
exercise it's a check meant a check am I
ready no you're probably not if you are
not motivated to eat right you're
probably having some kind of stress on
anxiety which you haven't picked up on
if you're not sleeping right these are
all behavior patterns that emerge when
your mental health is interlining so
it's important not only to to focus on
making that better for yourself
but also important to focus on whether
that's changed in any way because if
it's changed in any way those are
triggers for you and I think you need to
setup non-negotiables if you want to be
successful through this lockdown
make sure you don't lock yourself down
by not focusing on the things that will
uplift you so you need to make yourself
non negotiables of timing scheduling
your well-being because well-being needs
to be scheduled and I think what we can
do now it's kind of you know you can put
your questions out there cuz we can take
them later and we can move on to the
next episode of things that you want to
talk about that's right but I love how
you put things across about the
self-care and how you do this
concentrate meditation recovery is
really really important in order to you
know settle yourself down calm down for
on better you first shock my next
subject of conversations gonna be about
the caregivers from the self-care like
we spoke were self-care but how about
the caregivers this is the most
difficult aspect at this point if you're
a primary caregiver I feel for you I
feel free really I do because it is a
juggling show out there it's not easy in
fact we're running a well-being
it's called well-being volunteers United
it has 600 volunteers on it and most of
our calls are from people who are
primary caregivers and really struggling
to find time really struggling to find
that balance and extremely nervous and
worried about the rest of the family so
there are a lot of indicators that have
highlighted of the bangla stress and
anxiety has really increased for people
who are prime
caregivers and it's not easy because you
have to make sure that you are
organizing yourself organizing time for
others in your family organizing time
for yourself like I said in terms of
self-care and organizing that space
within the family circuit to have
meaningful conversations the other thing
I feel for our people who are primary
caregivers primary owners as well
because for them it becomes really
important to juggle their job with what
is going on in the house and spouses are
not really good right now to understand
that you need to spend not only spouses
but even your family members about how
much time you need to spend at work
because they need your help as well
because now the download in the house is
so much more you know initially of
course you're used to your children
going to school and goes to your your
family members doing the whole thing
really convening only over meals and how
you have them all the time and you need
to entertain specially if you do not
want your children to be on the iPad all
the time you are going to be struggling
if you do not want your if you do not
want your your elders to go out and you
do not want your elders to to feel the
impact of loneliness you are going to
need to be involved these aspects really
create a massive burden but there are
ways and that's the great part there are
ways to to kind of sort of strategize
the situation there are ways to beat up
your family system for this period and
that really makes you powerful in order
to deal with this situation it is like
running a business everything that we
have to do during Ovid is reimagining
dismantling the past we mantling the
present and imagining how to build a
safe system for yourself where you are
giving enough to love family members so
some of the things that I think you need
to pay attention to is really
communicate with your family members
open
about the challenges about what you need
to do about our time limitations and
beta schedule together
don't be dogmatic and tell them what you
want to do but really communicate work
on some kind of coping techniques and if
you find that you are irritable you're
losing your temper because you don't
have the space you don't have the time
work on the coping strategies that we've
already talked about in self-care you
know practice your recovery which is not
only sleep but meditation or mindfulness
music spend time if you can even just
walking on the spot just spend that time
with yourself because it's important for
you to develop that coping technique if
you feel overburdened because there's a
lot of issues taking place with the
talent pool in your home you need to
make sure that you give yourself a break
where you set up two special dates with
your partner or with your family members
it could be date night it could be game
night it could be game night with your
children it could be on it could be your
just interacting with them on story time
or it could be talking to your getting
your elders to talk to you and tell you
stories
anything you do just make sure that
communication becomes open any set time
for that it could be even be once a week
but as long as you're giving that time I
think that there is a good sort of idea
for them to motivate and mobilize
themselves to be able to aid you because
it becomes a supportive team right right
I like the point again I know and
because it spoke about you know spouses
and the family members my next question
is going to be addressed towards the
relationships now that's you know what
very important criteria that one will
look at it so what is your take on
relationships in the scenario this again
has been really tortured okay I will be
candid because most people will want to
say you know will not want to be candid
but we've had because we have a life
pulse on really what's happening in
India there is a lot of intimate
terrorism mistake
there is there feelings of no escape so
even though we are as a function of the
of humanity we believe in community but
being embedded the whole time in this
kind of conversation this kind of
consistent you know feedback of your
partner with yourself or your parents
with you or I'm just going to take the
primary relationship our point of view
there's a lot of stress in it people are
demanding extra time people do not have
that extra time people do not want to
communicate actively because
communication has become or hand become
in the past functional now communication
in this state can be functional anymore
it needs to be uplifting because you are
all in a situation together and that
means you have to change your
communication style you have to make it
more conducive to the environment it is
you have to make sure that so a lot of
times people are recognized now take it
time to spend with the partners at home
all the time they recognize that you
know maybe maybe some of the ideology of
life didn't match maybe some of their
thoughts about their future don't match
anymore so there's a lot of it's almost
like what we call in our sense a sort of
existential crisis I think a lot of us
are going through an existential crisis
where we're really questioning what our
relationship brings to us how does it
add value this comes with a silver
lining because you can communicate and
add value to each other by giving each
other that space by giving each other
that time by giving each other that
quality of conversation and
communication versus the quantity donors
you just because you are there you know
your relationship is done and it's gonna
be successful it's not you need to put
into that relationship positivity and
fuel it to be able to bring to use
something that's positive because now
you only have each other and it also has
also got to live because I've been doing
these talks and a lot of people have
said yeah
you've actually knowledge now to spend
time with our children and you know
we're not like parents who are remote
control parents because we've been there
and it's really made people understand
who their children are made them
reassess how to function with their
children as well so I think
relationships have taken a little bit of
a jolt and I think you know please as a
warning if you feel that you are losing
control and losing your temper and
becoming violent and if you feel like if
you feel on the other hand that you're a
victim of violence please reach out to
the help lines that are available
because they can help you understand how
to deal and cope with the situation
better and it's important because
there's no shame in fact the polar
foundation works on silence thorough and
every time I finish something I'm like
silence towards or saguru because hidden
agendas things that you keep within you
Fester they become bigger and they blow
up in your own face please help yourself
and the only way you can help yourself
is by reaching out walking away from
situations that do not benefit you and I
do not mean escape into another place
working in your mind to make sure that
you can walk away from situations like
that I like you said kiha acting up
under a Caleb Miedema can there at the
monkey and there you have God's other
body Carnevale hey Toph it please go
speak it out of Nepali marcbot
EJ up into suzumebachi ji but make sure
you speak it out because when you speak
it out it kind of lightens your heart
and thought and makes little more stable
am i right ready so I would suggest you
speak to of course you could talk to
your friends exact route but you would
get you want in a mirror you will get it
because they all have biases you will
get any mirror when you talk to somebody
who has no bias and that is why we talk
to me the help lines are free you can
talk to counselors and and volunteers
who've been trained to be able to deal
with this only because they will show
you your quad like I'll give you an
example okay now that you brought this
up I'm talking to you you're my friend
and I say yeah you know I've had a
really bad day I don't know our husbands
always shopping and you'll say to me I
know what's wrong with them even my
husband carries on with this whole
situation the light the monoculars have
gone to that person it's not on you
anymore
counsellor is rate so
I totally understand what you're going
through it seems to be a really
difficult situation so tell me what
really is happening in this situation
that you weren't I did defend the
understanding I make sure that you I
have a mirror in your own life and the
lens takes you deeper and deeper to the
crevices to understand what is your part
in this issue and what is creating
disharmony to get Ally a hatchet Kamini
what's the porn an adult Julie said you
know I have a lot of questions on these
subject but I will take the little later
on a Q&A I want to go ahead it spoke
about self-care caregivers of course
relationship and one goal is more
towards the work integration you take on
work-life integration what you suggest
and how to go about it so I wanna
highlight I call it work like
integration because you know not have
any work-life balance at this point time
is eluded you know we are doing things
that we wouldn't be doing chair but I'm
651 we're still here right or we may
still be your o'clock 9 o'clock 10
o'clock because there is no such thing
as work-life balance anymore but
work-life integration again going back
to number one
scheduling schedules your time
effectively keep a dashboard for
yourself in that time schedule your
self-care schedules your meetings
mixtures are not isolating yourself make
sure you are able to communicate with
people make sure that the savior that
you have which is your ability to to
deal with the situation is based on the
foundation of organization because the
moment it is organized you know when you
need to you know be there for your
family when you need to go there for
launch when you need to make sure you
can help you know when you need to make
sure you can help with the dishes you
haven't talked you know somebody who's
the other thing I was speaking to said
what you doing he's a yoga oh sure I
don't know
I mean he's not trouble you tell me -
alright but this is what it needs what
it needs but also work-life balance
means despite all that how do you make
sure that you have that conversation
with HR telling them that this is your
schedule HR has to be a little more
flexible in understanding what
really are some of the key areas for
them what are the key areas for their
for their employees and and really how
other employees placed and how do they
negotiate this time for themselves how
can they help them sort of utilize
technology to be able to work with the
new situation because technology has
played a major role now if you are an
employer you still have to have
work/life integration you still have to
recognize that your governance is very
important high quality of governance
really makes the attrition rate you know
extremely low in these cases we want to
make sure that that communication is
clear as well because when you have
clear communication your employee needs
everything longer they feel like they're
in this war or battle or situation
together you understand that town halls
need to be had you need to you need to
really bring them together really form
that community because that community
will help them fine-tune their own
capabilities to give back and with that
there are some tips that you need to go
through at all times make sure that when
you have that time and I've already
spoken about the sort of scheduling of
time with your with your member with the
members in your house avoid distractions
and that time please keep your phones
our way or on or or if you have whatsapp
I think the best way to use whatsapp is
we need to have it on your computer
screen so you're not constantly going
somewhere else any social media schedule
no time for it don't do it at the time
that you need to do it don't do it at
the time that you need to do work set
yourself break reminders one of the
things that I recommend highly is the
Pomodoro Tom's which is really you know
it's like a pasta sauce that has a lot
of big chunks of tomorrow in the same
way you realize those chunks of tomorrow
like those chunks of time where you know
who that you are the most focused use
that time to really integrate what is
essential
using the 80/20 Pareto principle but the
80% of work that you need to accomplish
utilize that 80% of work by giving your
says that time that that extremely
efficient time in those Pomodoro chunks
marry the two and work on that at that
point to make sure that you are capable
of doing the work that you need to do
these are all strategies and
unfortunately these take me five days to
teach people but I've given you a short
stack snippet of how do you make sure
you have all the boxes ticked to make
your life easy in these days well I'm
sure I'm just noting down all the points
and some important points no if you just
should do things and keep things off
distraction keep it focus it really does
wander thank you so much forget about
that point dimension right now I'm gonna
just go and do a couple of more last
questions that we discuss what's beyond
lockdown now as we see like for so many
people across the world what is beyond
lockdown great question it's a question
that's the question of the hour I think
that there is a myth at this point to
assume that be on lockdown means
everything's going to go back to square
one it is not going to go back to square
one you may still be doing the elbow
shakes you may not come very close to
people you may still be going through
grief you may still be going through an
emotional and you may still be going
through financial crisis you may still
be feeling helplessness but I don't want
to be the bearer of bad news there is
good news this silver lining that I have
seen given this epidemic pandemic has
really bought me to understand that
everybody here is fighting a common
enemy
we are only fighting a common enemy we
are also understanding that we all are
going through the same thing there is a
community which is larger than our homes
now we're reaching out to people far
more than we did before even like
through webinars such as these which are
open to the public as well you know
there's there is there are people who
have started to think about the mental
health which was never understood before
it was a stigma
this is allowing us to have those
generative conversations it's allowing
us to kind of build our psychological
framework to be able to deal with those
changes that are required you need to
and will always need to focus on
yourself you will need to focus on
communication verbal you will need to
understand how to build your work
technology know-how to be able to deal
with the masses what I love by the way
is that this is also brought to light
then women I know I love women okay
but women can and will be given an equal
place now in any job because everybody
is realized that you can be operating at
your optimal level even when you're
working from the house or when you have
sexy time and I think that is a really
really important part beyond covenant
that is going to come back home in fact
organizations may actually spend less
now because they may not need to have a
big swanky offices they may actually be
able to have meeting rooms and may be
able to work from the home I mean people
need pants for him the way we've been
operating in minot you may want to
actually spend more time with the family
yet because you've not how to you may
actually need to shift the way in which
you've been thinking to understand what
the triggers when the past that may not
be applicable now this is time for a new
change this is time for a new way and
there is no way that this would have
happened without this Gobert and I mean
we already know that the earth has
regenerated in this time the pollution
is gone we're breathing better even
though of course Cooper is there but
there is there is so much positivity
that's also come so brace yourself of
course for the changes be open and
flexible for the changes and build your
resources of of technology build your
resources of your own self value
self-worth and connect feel the
connection online and offline and when
you go offline make sure you follow the
Indian tradition of namaste and you do
not hug anybody immediately because you
still do not know what
lies in the person that is a carrier but
is not visible so please make sure that
you you understand the the ancient
Indian ethos was built to actually
prevent ourselves from falling ill in
times like these and if you just go back
to our lessons I think we are already in
good stead we are actually coming back
home that's true that's lovely said I
like I will just mention you know
utilization was disconnecting the world
in people and emotions and the crisis is
reconnecting emotions and people and
family together I have one question that
is object but so important and I know
most of the people will question me on
this but every time the log down is
about to get you get over it gets
extended and those million thoughts or
happiness again constrained to the
thought again what next so I won't know
your answer to this thoughts and how can
one get over the thoughts so so there is
an ABC model of counseling that works
really well for this you have an
activating event activating event is the
Co bit you have a B which is a belief
system okay you have a C which is the
consequence and stuck at home I'm in
lockdown you can't change it you can
change C so you can't change the
activating event and you can't change
the consequence you can only change your
belief system and what that really means
is how do I change my belief system I
say to anybody who says this to me I am
so frustrated I don't know what's
happening I want to make sure that this
ends I say what a hundred percent of
your frustration and anger in that and
why don't you put 100 people's
frustration and anger in that and tell
me does it change the situation it
doesn't
so why aggravate yourself because if you
have no control over it there is an
internal locus of control things that
you have control over my thoughts my
feelings my attitude my behavior my
reactions you have control over this you
do not have control over things that are
happening around you including your
spouse and their behavior including a
child in their behavior you only have
that limited area of control and I want
you to recognize the the limited nature
of your control so that you can be happy
and you know I want to tell you this
really uh on the side I have had three
kids my first kid was a premature baby
my second kid because my first kid came
only my second kid I was on bed rest for
seven or seven and a half months I
couldn't go to my brother's wedding
because I was on bed rest
okay now imagine my plight cuz it talked
to selling me fvb but no it makes me to
be able to get up and walk okay next
week we'll be able to do this seven a
half months on a bed that looks like
this head down legs are four seven tons
and you know what kept me alive the fact
that it is going to end at some point
afterwards the baby's gonna come out
healthy and if this is also for your own
health and safety and I think don't
doubt that go with the flow because
eventually things will get better and so
all you need to do is change that belief
system in the middle and sometimes we
are forced to recognize the limitations
of our own oh god like notion of I can
change everything into everything you
get to question that and just change
what you can change which is your own
thoughts made sure they become more
positive because it's only for your own
protection and not for anybody else's
rightly said believe you need to believe
someday everything will get better fine
at its best and exactly what progress is
told us right now thank you so much for
addressing so many subjects of us from
self care to caregivers relationship
work integration of course you on
lockdown that's really amazing now let's
get into the Q&A because I see the it's
been plotted right now with questions so
are we ready properly with questions oh
is always ready okay let's bring the
first question the question here is from
Daphne she's asking I am feeling anxious
these days though a family is with me I
can't share my stress of being stuck
indoors with them what do I do
laughing that's a great in fact 90% of
people are going through that they're
really frustrated with their parents by
the way the really frustrated me Arun
frustration is definitely a norm of what
people are facing so there is no shame
in what you're going through number one
number two you have to address what it
is that's causing you the frustration so
it's not the activating event of being
stuck at home with your parents but
something about that situation that's
causing the aggravation and so therefore
once you identify what is that situation
could it be giving you examples could it
be I find it very irritating that my
conversation is always overheard I find
it very irritating you know so you pick
what really is causing I find it very
irritating that I have to I don't have a
life of my own and I have to be there
whenever food is served
could be simple things like this I mean
things that trigger the anger or the
frustration of the annoyance is what you
need to deal with you do not need to
deal with the global scenario because
activating event and consequence like I
said will always be there and will be me
so that belief system which is you know
what is it that's causing this pain and
then you crash all causing this millions
or causing this stress that you question
is it worth me losing my sense of of
well-being by being angry about that one
thing that you've you that you found is
a trigger so is it worth my I take for
example my annoyance at eating at the
same time that everybody else wants to
eat okay now I say is it valuable to me
to be annoyed by that or is it better
for me to have a conversation about how
this is really bothering me and how I
would need more space like I said open
communication or is it okay for me to be
flexible here at this point there are
three different things that you can do
in this situation
and you can work on each and say and do
pros and cons or SWOT analysis on this
and see which one works the best for you
so don't judge the in xiety don't judge
the the feelings that you're going
through don't judge the behavior that
comes up because nobody going through
any kind of anxiety you're going to go
through irritability anger may be hot
arbitrations swag all kinds of things
happen with stress don't judge all that
judge whether this situation is it
important enough for you to lose your
well-being over because this is
well-being 360 and you do not need to
lose your well-being over something that
is inconsequential when you can make a
change move the irrational thoughts to
the rational move you're helpful or
unhelpful thoughts to helpful by making
sure you address the problem by having
open very clean communication not
aggressive may be assertive at times
that's it
right Lisa Daphne I hope you got your
answer
our next question is about from Ducie
Street questions my office work has
increased multipole add to that my
family demands my time how do i Coppa
and keep the balance yeah Julie like I
said scheduling is the only mantra you
have to schedule and in that schedule
keep it dashboard for the whole week
because you don't have to do everything
today you know what is the most
important thing that needs to come
forward you know I mean trends a great
tool to use by the way if you wanna use
Trello or whatever you have internally
scheduling tools or to-do lists
internally as well but schedule in your
dashboard things that you can move to
the next day things that you can move to
the third date so that your whole week
map of the week is in front of you and
in that like I said right in the
beginning schedule time for your family
as well because of course they all
worked on together and you are not alone
anymore this is in fact this is the time
despite the fact that they're saying
it's loneliness and all that this is the
time that you are not alone so you know
really schedule and people will
understand I just love that point
remember you're not alone there is
family as well and even they must be
doing the same thing it's your time to
be there so I
I hope this already answer my next
question is from Raj who's questioning
I'm a frequent traveler this lockdown is
make me feel irritated how do I reduce
my irritation I'm a frequent traveler
and I am feeling the same way but when
you can't change the facts and the
future you can only know one thing
within yourself understand that maybe
this will change you know one of the
things I've been thinking about I mean
this is off like the I mean I can't even
say off the record could streaming but
even after they lock down unless they be
dropping down things for everybody to
kind of have safe air
I'm not really sure how long it's going
to be till the flights I may be safe and
if and I told my son about this is 14
then I was like you're actually really
frustrated this lovely frustration so he
said you know if you really want to
travel just get on a bike and bike
around maybe he will get that like
feeling you know there are different
things we can do so you might my lights
have gone so in case I drop off let me
know so there are some things that you
can do to make it easier for yourself
and there are some things that you can
too so you can control when the flights
up and get activated you can to show
that you can definitely surf on the net
to different areas and see what that
looks like what your next destination
would be you know keep a kind of a
record for what you wanna do like on
bucket list for once this is over Julie
said you know Me's gonna have this
add-on to your answer right now when I
travel quite frequently and for the
first time I have got a perfect shed
you'll in my life would have no hat over
the last 15 years so take it back away
that you can actually schedule your life
and make a lot of changes for your body
for your mental well-being and for your
wellness and with your family I think
that's also best way to go about it so I
hope Raj you go to answer and if you
still want to travel travel your kitchen
your balcony your bedroom your question
it's coming from Anjali many people
around me are losing jobs getting salary
curves how do I stay away from these
billions of negative thoughts around me
including coronavirus yeah that's a
really good question and really uh you
know very valid there are companies that
are going through this cut down there is
this is the worst economic crisis of the
century almost I mean it's really bad
worse than 1930 and it's not gonna get
better anytime soon
it's gonna take a while there is the
negativity again you have to question
whether you negativity is going to help
you feel positive to be able to build
your resources to be able to sort of
grow in your
in your capability for the next job that
you may want to get or is it going to
help you hungry I know that this
lockdown has caused so many people to
feel overwhelmed with the situation and
helpless ready and and totally hopeless
but there is nothing that like I keep
saying we cannot change the situation
and in fact it's also very difficult for
for employers because they've also now
suddenly started to your analyze that
budgets really look at the a chart
performances the KPI is really see who's
measuring up and who's not and cutting
down on the people that were not
measuring up because before we were just
would just carry them along with us you
know and because we didn't have those
pressure off of cutting people down we
cannot beat them because the patrician
and and attrition rates if they're high
it's really breeds badly for the company
but now they're really getting to assess
that so yes if the performance was bad
or the performance was substandard or
even the performance is really good but
the company can't support it that is
going to happen there are going to be
cut downs but there's also a completely
complete openness to new businesses jobs
entrepreneurship ideas that are coming
up people are becoming self-employed
really fast and if you have a skill if
you have a talent hold on that and if
you don't have a skill and a talent
learn something at this point because
you may have a little bit more time to
do some webinars even the Harvard
Business School is giving so many free
workshops and webinars and I think that
I mean all the universities really are
take some of those really understand
what it is that you might want in your
next leg of life uses it as an
opportunity rather than a threat because
we need was for analysis you know you
have strengths you know you have
weaknesses you know that you have
opportunities and you know that you have
threats and this threat you can't change
your strengths you you can grow the
opportunities are available seek them
out find them I remember when I was in
Canada and I was moving from a banking
kind of job to doing the mental health I
remember you know doing myers-briggs
doing
sort of personality assessments to see
whether my idea of what I wanted to
build at that point my neighbor miss
consulting wasn't really marrying my
sort of psyche and when I realized it
did I just chucked everything up and
took that strength for myself to build
my own company so really utilize these
times you know we can actually have a
long conversation about this whole
subject if I'm not run faculty and we
can also have another episode altogether
about moving from a banking towards a
mental health that can be another
subject of conversation for stocks
however the question I have a lot of
questions I want to ask you as well
about Miss Reed remove it from the the
chat room there is no balance between my
work and home life I managed to eat only
once a day being at home how do I bring
about a balance question from Sudan shoe
you know a sedan should lovely question
you're going to have to balance it
yourself he did one meal a day I know
I'm gonna say this out loud but he
didn't one meal a day is not a bad idea
give it the fact that we're not burning
that much but make sure it's nutritious
snacking in the middle bit like maybe
some maybe some nuts if you can get your
hand on that so if you can get your hand
on some kind of foods keep that handy
but one really big cooked meal should be
enough at this point because we're
really not burning that much energy so
the work light which we were talking
about you're talking more about the fact
that it was really difficult for you
because you're doing that much then
apart from setting your boundaries which
is something that you need to do which
is why in the work light thing I said
you know talk to HR set up the
boundaries tell them how much I need
India tell them how much time you can't
give given the circumstance or HR has to
be able to go flexible at this point and
because corporate governance matters and
there has been this is a pandemic this
is not an irregular situation so you do
have the support of that but really
don't push yourself to a breakdown
because it's not worth the lock down and
say not worth it so you need to focus on
on really like I said to the lady who's
who asked me a question before really
focus on what you need to get done and
schedule your time
using dashboards effectively make sure
you're not overextending yourself you're
getting enough rest you're getting
enough sleep and you are eating
nutritious food even if the cooks meal
is one today you are getting nutrition
throughout the day with seeds nuts
fruits and those kind of things and do
not drink too much caffeine do not get
into alcohol and and drugs do not do any
of those things did you want to add any
value they will be depleting your energy
and you know I know everybody
vaccinations to you for actually having
a healthier lifestyle
that's what lunch to make sure you have
planning eat eat eat at least not once
not twice thrice mandatory one last
question I will take a priority from the
chat box and then maybe I can ask my own
questions a couple of them if we still
have time
Brenda somebody from Mumbai called urban
is asking living in Mumbai is one of the
densest cities in the world not many are
used to distance and space the social
distancing would stay poor over
well quite some time how important is
social conditioning for our future and
how can I do my bit oh well do not focus
on social distancing focus on the fact
that there is no emotional distancing at
this point okay
social distancing is something that has
to be done emotional distancing is
something that we do not do we do not
have I know Bombay because I live in
Bombay I'm not living there right now
but I live in Bombay primarily and it's
very very important to be safe at this
point people need to enter that is why a
lot of people Allah and the government
there as well is a lot of awareness
being built on the importance of social
or other physical distancing because
physical distancing is mandatory to be
safe or to be able to cut this down
please ensure it physical distancing and
in fact if you have means to social
media make sure you spread the word make
sure you are giving box okay every
single person needs to be you know a
really strong voice in the physical
distancing specially for Mumbai because
it has become clearly
most dangerous cities by the way in fact
India has the very very no rates of
death given the covalent given our
population we're doing really well but
in any case from our original vision it
seems to be a lot but definitely do not
do not try to you know break the
obviously not break the laws but but do
not try to do that also because it's
really just for your own well-being and
everybody else's well-being we do not
know who the carriers are even if
they're not just being the science right
so we've got to be very very careful and
and don't rush into I want to make sure
that we know this I can go to work
because the moment you get in that
elevator and somebody sneezes you have
no idea what you're in for
I can totally connect to what you're
saying right now cuz you know this is a
feeling and people across I'm hearing
news that people are getting hit or
belted by a group of people because one
is sneezing or coughing that's that's
really scary so I think it's a process
that will take some time and I'm sure
one day we'll all get better and the
earth will heal and people here will
heal better so I I have so many question
that I want to ask you personally but I
think time is it constrain here so I'm
not sure how many question I can ask you
but just one question I will ask you on
a one-to-one basis here that practically
you know what all this being at home
with family time working what I'm seeing
as an observation in my own house that
you know people are on social media more
than the usual they were yeah after the
lockdown is over you know will this
impact your mental well-being media from
Ludo blink Ludo on different apps to
candy crush - you know Instagram
Facebook things you know it's like
saying that in guro market or shop and
you pick up chips you pick up chocolate
you pick up you know you pick up all the
all the stuff that's there that's German
food you have options of healthy food as
well on the net you know don't go for
the junk don't go for this because this
adjectives what you're talking about
what people are doing is addictive it is
classified as an addiction or any
wh-words well you want to make sure that
you are stringent in what you want to
look at what you want to feel what you
want to take in everything that you take
in bodies everything that you take in is
reprogramming you to a level every
single day even this what we're doing
it's reprogramming you in some way you
are getting trained there is there are
two things that happen so you've got
genes and you've got conditioning genes
I don't change conditioning is getting
altered every single minute of the day
by the things you accept and the things
you reject please reject things that are
not healthy for you please reject that
social media of I him to look good and
to look like this and I mean whatever it
is that you doing because it's not
healthy for you you are complete already
in yourself and self-care is not about
that photo that shows me that you are
working on self-care it is really about
what you're doing there is no need to
get on to of course if you need like a
little bit of a laugh and one tick tock
one one tick tock is no way kill you
because of moderation is the key here
but you do not want to wake up and I see
with my children I have their own we
wake up in the morning especially early
so he can get on his computer on his
iPad without me being there because he
plays and I'm like oh my god you cannot
do this first you will have a bath this
circuit proves you have to set up rules
Phyllis l you cannot you schedule that
time so when you want to schedule that
time to do rubbish schedule that time
because yes it may help you in summer
but it cannot and should not you get 125
expert be there all day please do not do
that schedule time for it
please do not they say and there's a
study that says one and a half hours and
no more I find one and a half hours so
it's too much but please one a half
hours and no more of this junk media
because it does like Madonna said it
because of which huge repercussions as
you as you finish this lockdown because
21 days to make a habit and 21 days to
make a habit you have already gone past
free mondays
don't and if that has become something
that you've been doing it will become an
habit
the other thing that has become a habit
is porn viewership and I want to and I
wanted you understand that all these
addictive things will have very serious
repercussions on your relationships with
people because if you are spending more
time on your social media and your your
tic TOCs and your your instagrams and
you are spending with the person who is
in front of you this is going to tell in
your relationship is going to tell you
communication you are going to become
aggressive in the way in which you
communicate because you want that space
to be able to do what you want it's
going to be fights is good it's gonna
trigger a cycle of unhappiness so back
to schedule that time and make sure
everybody knows what time you scheduled
for it you have no clue how happy I am
practically having a conversation with
you it's really taught me a lot I'm sure
it's also inform all our viewers who are
watching us about how you can take
control and as we discuss this it's for
you to only get better wait here with
wellness 360 make sure you make the most
of it here with ICS hello Bart thank you
so much property I can have it I can
have a whole day of chat with you on
mental will be so much time will
constrain here but thank you so so much
for joining us here and wellness me 60
at home bye I see a Salem bar and you
are an amazing person who moved from a
serious banking to get into a very very
serious business of mental and took your
so many life I must say thank you so
much from the bottom of my heart and
thank you so much in practicing all
right that was put out there giving you
an insight about how you can take charge
of your own mental well-being and make
sure you riding over it and being the
best you can ever be
it's all for you to become completely
well so this is wellness 360 at home and
we want you all to be the best of the
best in all criteria possible my name is
Nathan apartheid
follow me on Instagram but make sure if
you
follow me also be at home stay at home
be positive be healthy that's exactly
what we want you all to do this is
wellness 360 at home brought you by
ICICI Lombard thank you for joining us
we'll see you in our next episode thank
you